So how would say a householder
you know with its life and duties and so
on
would they be able to practice
mindfulness of the body rightly
>> like according to you how would you
explain to them what mindfulness of the
body is? Well, they can practice it if
they fulfill certain requirements that
will essentially undo all the things that
essentially undo all the things that
cover up the body for them.
>> Mhm.
>> That's why the Buddha was only teaching
mindfulness of the body to
like 99% of the time to monks. And
whenever he taught it to lay people,
it's people who already had the right
view. So if you want to be able to um
see that body, you have to be emulating
those principles
that will stop covering up the body.
>> Mhm. Yeah. Because there was there were
sutas where it was said that four
setatanas could be used to develop the
right view.
>> Yeah. But if those sutas were taught to
monks, so people who were
>> established in a certain conduct
and that conduct the relevance of that
conduct is
>> uh it is what allows the body to be
discerned. Doesn't cover it up anymore.
>> So what what's covering it up?
>> Uh well actions rooted in greed and
aversion, not keeping the precepts.
not keeping the precepts.
>> Mhm.
So acting out against the precepts
covers up the body.
>> Yeah. Even if you make all the effort in
the world to see it within, you're
breaking up the precepts that
>> you won't be the body you're looking at.
>> Yeah. Those actions cover it up simply
by being done.
>> And uh say if you are not doing those
actions, but you are not making the
effort to see it,
>> would that uncover it? If you truly are
disengaged from all of those actions,
even by mind, then yes, the body would
be uncovered.
>> And what is how do I disengage? So, I'm
keeping the presets, but how do I
disengage by mind?
>> Well, it's
it's you want to see not just specific
directions of action, but anything where
a certain
>> What do you mean specific directions?
speaks just practically
>> like the precepts you don't want to just
think oh okay I'm not killing I'm not
stealing um celibate and all this and
then everything else is fine
>> mhm
>> you want to al when
>> everything else not defined by the
precepts is fine I shouldn't be seeing
that I shouldn't be thinking that
>> yeah you shouldn't be thinking that just
because it's not against the precepts
it's fine
>> it's fine uhhuh so what then constitutes
fine and not fine
>> well you want to see what's your
intention or your mental state behind
doing it
>> or attending to
examples. >> So let's say
>> So let's say
take somebody who is established in the
precepts but then is doing one of these
um breath focusing absorption practices
u that are very popular today. And they
don't realize that that very attempt to
attend and and concentrate and focus is
based on a certain mental pressure.
>> Mhm. that mirrors exactly the same
principle of sensuality and and like the
precepts that
>> but what if somebody says well I have no
pressure to do it doing it you know
because it's neutral uh pleasant calming
>> but what happens if you don't do it
>> what's the problem with that well
nothing happens if I don't do it
>> well
>> but I choose to do it is there a problem
in doing it neutally
>> the problem still is even if it's
neutral that's not the place where you
will find the body because the body is
not at the level of sensations
So the the say the sensation the
internal sensations of the breath
>> mh
>> the the say the the the whole kind of
sense of breathing that I'm attending to
>> is not the body.
>> No those are just tactile sensations and
then there's no they don't have any
special significance just because of the
position where they are.
So then if if um if um attending to your
breath is not where the body is,
>> why did the Buddha teach the mindfulness
of breathing in order to develop the
mindfulness of the body?
>> Well, because the Buddha wasn't nowhere
in the in the Anaponosati
uh descriptions does it talk about
sensations. It doesn't talk about it
doesn't even talk about breathing as
something that you observe. It talk it
talks about it as an action something
that you train in.
>> So it's not about it at no point does it
say that it's about attending.
>> Mhm.
>> So what is it about then?
>> Well, it's about maintaining the
perspective of the actual body that's
the basis for your attention while
you're acting through breathing.
>> So maintaining the perspective of the
actual body. What is the actual body
then? Well, once that actual body has been
Well, once that actual body has been
it's it's that
basis for your entire domain of your six
senses that's left
>> again that's just getting too abstract
now >> it's practically speaking I want to be
>> it's practically speaking I want to be
mindful of the body I read the
mindfulness of the breathing suta you're
telling me I shouldn't be attending to
breath should know the basis or
something but like what okay I'm not
attending to the breath what do I do to
see that body.
>> Well, it's not something that you do.
It's not a positive [snorts] object that
you can clarify through some effort.
It's something that has to be uncovered.
>> Okay. So, what how do I uncover it?
>> Well,
having assumed that you're then
establishing the precepts as we said.
>> Okay. I take on the precepts.
>> Yeah.
>> Um I take on as you said, uh just
because it's not against the precept
doesn't mean it's not an obstruction. So
I recognize the intentions, the
pressures, the compulsions even towards
seemingly good things, but I don't do it
because it's rooted in the wrong things.
>> Anything else? Or would that mean like
I'm now seeing the body correctly?
>> If you're established in that, yes,
>> and even if I don't make the effort to
see it,
>> well, you have to make effort to not do
the things that will cover it up. You
don't have to make effort to see it as a
>> Yeah. So that's what I'm asking. Yeah.
>> So then if I'm established in these
modes of behavior rightly
>> not just keep the precepts in that
external sense um and um
and you know I have a I have um
cuz I've been like say following what
you say listening the talks reading the
writings I'm keeping the precepts practicing
I'm keeping the precepts practicing
sensor train but I also have a obviously
a strong
urge hope that that will reveal the body
to me.
>> Yeah. Well, if you
>> is that fine.
>> Acting out of it is not fine.
>> Acting out of that strong compulsion
comp hope
>> to find the body. Yeah.
>> You have to not deny it and try to get
rid of it, but you have to see.
>> So, if I'm doing all the practices you
describe and I can't help can't help but
hope that that's going to reveal the the
true body to me,
>> um I shouldn't be acting out of that
either. No, you should include it just
as you were including all the other
things like pressure to break the
precepts arose.
>> How do I include it? How do I include my
hope to see the because you know it's
like a factual goal I'm striving to.
>> So how do I include that goal of seeing
the body correctly and not falling into
a a trap? How do I include it?
>> By not acting out of it.
>> How do I act out of it?
uh
taking it for granted and starting to do
things out of that hope.
So the hope that I feel towards that
body being this revealed to me,
>> trying to clarify it, trying to see it
more, trying to uh rehash your ideas
about it, all of that, you're taking up
that hope.
>> So intentionally choosing to sort of um
>> mentally kind of push down further.
>> Yeah. Um so then if say okay I don't do
that now
>> is that enough do I just what do I do
just stay with that or
>> well so not not acting on the body not
acting on speech recognizing mental
intentions and now the pressuring hope
of seeing the body rightly because you
know ultimately I want to be free from
suffering >> I recognize that pressuring compulsion
>> I recognize that pressuring compulsion
as a trap
>> uh you mentioned I don't try to get rid
of it
>> I don't act out of it as in like okay
I'm going to rehash this and and keep
thinking about it so it gets quicker.
>> Um, so I don't do that either.
>> Then what?
>> Well, you need to protect that because
other things will be coming up that will
be trying to absorb you out of pressure.
>> Mhm. So then Okay. So then protecting it
from being recovered, so to speak.
>> Yeah.
>> Covered again.
>> Cuz it's not a once and done deal. other
things like it's it's as the Buddha said
in one suta, it's like mara trying to
grab a footing through whichever sense
object it can to get you to act out.
>> Mhm.
>> So it's not like you just oh you did
everything and you just sit down and
forget about it. It's something that you
have to protect.
>> So if I'm um if I'm protecting it
um patiently
>> Mhm.
presumably for as long as it takes.
Can I then do the mindfulness of
breathing? Can I then do the pronati?
>> Well, if it if it's
if it's not again coming out of a
central expectation
>> that you have from it and you're just no
I just want to
further um push f push further.
>> Okay. So if it's coming out of the
expectation, >> it's
>> it's
it's it's a wrong practice.
>> You should not do the the right form of
anapanasi that the Buddha described.
>> So how do I do the right one
if you are
>> I do have expectation?
>> Yeah.
>> So does that mean I cannot do
anapanasati? Well, you shouldn't do it
with the expectation like as a hoping
like okay sure the expectation is there
but if I just do the practice somehow
will sort it itself out.
>> No you have to
>> don't add on top of it.
>> Yeah the practice is in regard to that
expectation not like
>> so how do I practice anapanosati in
regard to the expectation that I have
from anapanosati. M
well it's
that's why I said before you the
practice hinges on you seeing that body
hinges on you seeing that body
>> as
>> okay well you could ask the same
question for the body I still have
expectation that the the actual body the
real body will be revealed
>> how do I p practice the um
revealing of the actual body protecting
of the actual body
with expectations of seeing the actual
body. >> Well, the thing is expectations being
>> Well, the thing is expectations being
there.
Expectations are risen and you acting
out of them are two separate things.
>> So,
>> so okay, so I'm not acting out.
>> Yeah.
>> But the expectation is there. But
anything I do on account of it wouldn't
that be like like back onto anapanati.
So I have the expectation that practice
of anapanasati would lead to certain
revelation insights and so on.
>> Uh I'm not acting out of it.
So I'm not doing it. But does that mean
I can't do anopanosati at all? I can't
approach mindfulness of the body through
breath because this expectation is in
the way because whatever I do would be
kind of rooted in that expectation.
>> Well, but that's thing expectation can
be there but you taking it for granted
hoping to get the result of it that
doesn't follow automatically. So if you
see that's what I'm asking. So I'm not
taking it for granted.
>> Uhhuh.
Um,
is there any other way I could relate to
breathing that would not be rooted in
that expectation or do I need to
completely abandon any notion of
practice of mindfulness of the body
through breathing?
So presumably I've clarified it to that
level through not acting out of body,
speech, mind, watching my intentions,
not taking for granted the desire to
clarify the body, not acting out of that
further passionately containing it.
Is that is that is that anati already or
can I do something actually that would
not necessarily automatically be coming
out of that expectation?
>> Well, you could undermine the
expectation. if you're seeing the body rightly. But
if you're seeing the body rightly. But
yes, so like we said, not acting out of
the expectation, seeing the body already
there, coming before it
and then breathing.
So seeing the body coming before an
expectation >> Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> that I have of seeing the body.
>> That can you explain that? I mean it's
>> well if you haven't been acting out of
the expectation
>> which because again even if you take
that up and then try to see the body
it's not going to work.
>> So that's there and then
what's revealed by you not taking
expectation for granted is that kind of
physical basis of you could say for
example your lungs being functional.
Mhm. >> It's not a theoretical idea you have to
>> It's not a theoretical idea you have to
clarify. It's like a
factual just just
state.
>> Mhm.
>> That even if you were to overlook it, it
would still be there and it's the entire
reason that you're alive. So you have to
you have to um that will become clear if
you haven't been acting out of all these
unh wholesome things and then
maintaining the let's say peripheral
sight of that fact of functioning lungs
you could say
>> breathing simultaneously with that
without overemphasizing one or the
other. >> So but I'm still doing the breathing.
>> So but I'm still doing the breathing.
>> You're doing it but with this at the
same time. You don't let the breathing
become the the kind of fully focused
concentrated effort.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Okay. It has to happen.
>> I'm not talking about necessarily as I
said in the coarsest
>> Yeah.
>> misguided ways of meditation technique.
>> But
again, the point is like is there a way
that I can do the breathing rightly
as a form of mindfulness of the body
practice? Yeah. So if you are balancing the two so
Yeah. So if you are balancing the two so
to speak, if you're not um trying to
over clarify,
>> it doesn't really say that you have to
balance breathing with anything else.
>> At no point do I need to set
prerequisites. >> Well, it says mindfully, mindfully he
>> Well, it says mindfully, mindfully he
breathes in, mindfully he breathes out.
>> Okay.
>> So there has to be
a knowledge while you're breathing, not
just the breathing.
>> Yes. So you need to do the breathing
but [snorts]
in a way that clarifies
that aspect because you're breathing all
the time
but this aspect is not being
discerned. >> So how do I do the breathing in order to
>> So how do I do the breathing in order to
clarify that aspect?
If whenever I do the breathing is rooted
in hope of the revelation of the aspect
well in the
like in that act of breathing
if you
don't focus on it too much.
>> Mhm. Having that hope or expectation
like we said you don't act out of it
this background domain
can be discerned
>> by not focusing too much on the
breathing. >> Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> So by doing it but not focusing on it.
>> How's that possible? How can be doing
something consciously without focusing
on what you're doing?
What constitutes too much?
Well, you're actively trying to make
that the only
thing in your experience. It's it's a
it's an extra effort that people make on
top to kind of
>> isolate this from everything else. And
that part is not necessary.
>> So, if I'm not isolating it,
>> yeah.
>> And I'm just doing it >> then
>> then
>> that's okay.
>> Yes.
as long as you keep sight on that
motivation like we said or that um
attitude behind it because the attempt
to try to isolate it doesn't necessarily
arise as an option. It's when those
expectations begin to arise and you
overlook them.
So
>> So that sounds kind of like a what
you're describing sounds like a
reference point.
Breathing becomes a reference point.
>> Yeah. Because reference point is
obviously not something you're directly
um refer um occupied with all the time.
It's just something that's placed that
then things are referred to as they
come. >> Yeah. So that's exactly why you wouldn't
>> Yeah. So that's exactly why you wouldn't
be able to make it an object because
then >> Well, I can make it an object. But
>> Well, I can make it an object. But
you're saying I shouldn't.
>> Yeah. No, you wouldn't be able to do it
rightly. >> Oh, right. Right. Right.
>> Oh, right. Right. Right.
>> Because it would cease to be a reference
point. If it becomes an object, it ceases to be
If it becomes an object, it ceases to be
a reference point.
>> So breathing as a practice of
mindfulness, if it's done as a
concentration practice or focusing
practice, it ceases to be a reference
point because it becomes an object.
>> Yeah.
>> And um but if that object as I said it's
neutral and it provides me with calm
overall factor, I'm calmer after I make
breathing my object.
>> Mhm. Could you remind me what the
problem with that is?
>> Well,
it's a problem if you think that that's
clarifying the satipan of the body.
>> So, it's not the body that I'm um it's
not the actual body that I'm
concentrating on
and the calm that I experience. It's not
the calm on account of establishing
inside. >> Yeah. Because just ask yourself after
>> Yeah. Because just ask yourself after
doing that calming practice like like we
said before if if your oxygen were to be
cut off
>> Mhm.
>> would that practice have made you
dispassionate in regard to that
possibility >> and
>> and
>> sorry I don't understand it
>> like if that calming focusing practice
you did
>> would that have made you imperturbable
in the face of your oxygen being
depleted? >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
Because this is to say the practice
ofati leads to aranchship. So it should
lead you to dispassion and non ownership
of that body. So yes factually like you
can do that but if you think that that's
the anopanosati that the Buddha thought
taught which would lead to that result
>> then obviously well you're missing out
on the actual result that you should be
looking for. So the calming that I get
on a kind of med making a um uh
breathing a meditation object
is not the um
well it's not something that would um
make me unafraid
of death
>> of death
which is the purpose of the practice. So
then that's not anapanati that in any if
if your definition of anapanati that is
that kind of focusing that is nothing to
do with the path anymore. So it's not
anapanati. >> Mhm. Mhm. So then um but say the
>> Mhm. Mhm. So then um but say the
knowledge
>> Mhm.
>> of the breath or the lungs or the heart
>> being possibly cut off at any given
point in the future. Would
that make me uh unafraid of death?
>> Well, yeah. You can see the direct
connection because as soon as you start
thinking about it, you see this, you'll
probably see this fear
>> and apprehension coming up. So you can
see, oh, this is exactly something that
I wouldn't want to think about,
something that I wouldn't want to
maintain clarity of
>> because it kind of has that jarring
aspect to it that it would it would be
easier just not to think about it even
if it is factually the case.
>> Mhm.
>> So like what guarantees
a successful thinking about it?
>> You know what I mean? So it's like I I
want to think about it but yes it's
jarring it's fright it's it's
frightening >> how do I make sure I
>> how do I make sure I
>> I do it rightly or it doesn't become too
much or
>> well that jarringness
should never take you to the point where
you start acting out and compromising
all the prerequisites that allowed you
to reveal and see this
>> prerequisites such as the
>> precepts sense restraint not acting out
of unh wholesome intentions even
mentally. >> So if I already have been doing that
>> So if I already have been doing that
training in that then when these jarring
pressures come to to run or panic on a
kind of um well on a kind of not being
moved by the prospect of death.
>> You don't compromise what you were
established in no matter what.
>> And that would help.
What what would how would that help?
Well, because
those the jarringness and and all the
kind of uh
>> intensity,
>> yeah, bad things that you might be
getting out of it, it's
maintained that way because in the past
whenever those fears would come up, you
would try to cover them up somehow.
>> So now if when that
>> So it's like the fear gets worse if you
run from it.
>> Yeah. That's how you maintain it. That's
how you stay afraid.
>> Yeah.
>> So if you don't run from it,
that fear would disappear.
>> Yeah. That you're it's like an exposure
therapy so to speak.
>> Mhm.
Yeah. I suppose. Yeah. So then if the
anopanasati were to be done like that then yeah
were to be done like that then yeah
indeed there is a direct connection
between not being afraid of death
and successful practice of anapanasi.
>> Yeah you would need to introduce a
second step of get the magical insight
of something else and then you become a
narat >> the simple absence
>> the simple absence
of fear would be a proof. Yeah. Absence
of fear in in relation to the body
breaking apart
>> like yeah the most kind of fundamental
threat to your existence.
>> And I guess yeah that will be calming in
and of itself
>> the fact that you cannot be afraid. M
>> so then that practice of anapanosati or
broad more broader practice of the
mindfulness of the body
just to recap would be then on the level
of
withdrawing yourself from unh wholesome
through keeping the precepts
uh restraining from sensuality
>> course by body sensuality
southless sensuality by speech
mental sensuality acting out of
>> hindrances in general
>> hindrances is in general.
So, um, and then discerning the
kind of the nature of what's left there
regardless of what you're hoping
>> to come out of it or not.
>> Cuz whether I hope or not
that breathing will reveal the body or
the restraint would reveal that which
actual body is. Whether I hope or not,
what's there is the body is there.
>> Yeah.
>> That well that which resulted in
withdrawal from sensuality is there. We
don't even have to call it the body.
Um the breath is there
>> whether I choose to do it or not, choose
to overdo it or not, underdo it or not,
the body is breathing
>> and the threat to its continuation is
also there at this point.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So you can always um connect
with it on the right level so to speak
indirectly >> if you're Yeah. not covering up through
>> if you're Yeah. not covering up through
all these other things. So, but what if
I'm doing these practices and there is
no fear coming up? >> Well,
>> Well,
>> am I doing something wrong or
>> not necessarily if you are sure
perfectly sure that you haven't been
doing all the if if all these
prerequisites of your behavior are well
established. >> Mhm. Then um
>> Mhm. Then um
>> if fear doesn't come up, you don't have
to then
like are you gonna become afraid of that
that fear isn't coming up and start like
>> trying to get get it back going. M
>> then you're putting your head into the
situation whereas the whole point is to
>> so if the fear is not coming up and I
recognize okay I'm not panicking on
account of that or feeling that I must
invoke the fear
>> then does that like protecting that
apply to this then you just protect it
>> yeah and then the fear might
>> see what comes up because then
>> see even in that moment where you
realize oh the fear isn't coming up you
might realize because that's moving you
now. Like you might those same
expectations we were talking about
before that would um pollute the entire
practice would be coming up right then
and there because you expect to
accelerate by getting more fear more
this more that but then that's exactly
what we said before would be covering up
the body.
>> Mhm.
>> So you have to contain that.
>> Yeah. Regardless of how it feels, the
pro the point of it is not to get a
specific experience out of it. The point
is to maintain that perspective
regardless of whatever comes up.
>> Okay. So it's not about a specific
experience regardless of the hope but
maintaining the whole setup.
>> Yeah. And that's going to feel
>> even if there is a specific experience.
>> Yeah.
>> Because there might be and the factory
probably will be to some extent.
>> Yeah. some degree of novelty, some
degree of revelations or insight.
That's not what I should emphasize. No,
>> you will fall from the practice if you
start emphasizing that.